Inventory of the Jesse Wendell Vaughn papers, 1865-1968
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Jesse Wendell Vaughn papers
1865-1968
Vaughn, Jesse Wendell, 1903-
00313
8.82 cubic feet (23 boxes)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Research material, correspondence, photographs, and manuscripts regarding the military actions between the United States Army and the Dakota and Cheyenne in 1876.
Biography of Jesse Wendell Vaughn
Jesse Wendell Vaughn was an author and historian of 19th century military campaigns in the U.S. West. Most of his work concerned the campaign against the Dakota and Cheyenne in 1876. Vaughn published books and articles, including "The Reynolds Campaign on Powder River," and "With Crook at the Rosebud."
Scope and Content
Collection contains research material used in the creation of Vaughn's books and articles, including correspondence (1865-1958), manuscripts, periodicals, newsletters, newspaper clippings, biographical papers, blueprints, and a scrapbook. Also included are photographs depicting sites of forts such as Fort Fetterman, Fort Laramie, and Fort Reno, as well as sites where battles took place.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on the materials for research purposes, and the collection is open to the public.
Related Materials
There are no known other archival collections created by Jesse Wendell Vaughn at the date of processing.
Additional Information
Partial finding aid available in repository.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by Jesse Wendell Vaughn in 1953 and Mrs. Jesse Wendell Vaughn in 1976.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of select material from this collection are available at http://digitalcollections.uwyo.edu:8180/luna/servlet/uwydbuwy~138~138.
Access Terms
Rosebud, Battle of the, Mont., 1876.; Cheyenne Indians -- Wars, 1876.; Dakota Indians -- Wars, 1876.; Wyoming -- History -- to 1889.; Wyoming -- History -- 1890 -1918.; Wyoming -- History -- 1919 -1945.; Battlefields -- West (U.S.); Fort Laramie National Historic Site (Wyo.); Fort Fetterman State Historic Site (Wyo.); Fort Fetterman (Wyo.); Fort Laramie (Wyo.); Fort Reno (Wyo.)
Arts, Humanities, and Social Sciences; Education; Military; Native Americans; Wyoming
Container List
- Series I. Correspondence and Writings of Jesse Wendell Vaughn
  - Correspondence of Jesse Wendell Vaughn, 1952-1968 (Box 1-2)
  - Galley Proofs of The Battle of Platte Bridge (Box 8)
  - Galley Proofs of The Reynolds Campaign on Powder River (Box 8)
  - Manuscript: "Indian Fights: New Facts on Eight Encounters" (Box 3)
  - Manuscript: "The Reynolds Campaign on Powder River" (Box 3)
  - Manuscript: "The Battle of Platte Bridge" by Jesse Wendell Vaughn (Box 3)
- Series II. Research Material
  - Blueprints - Factory Building, 1937 (Box 11)
  - Blueprints - State School for the Deaf, 1937 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence (photocopies and transcripts) of United States War Department, participants, area residents, and other historians, 1865-1946 (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts (transcripts) concerning the U.S. Military on the frontier and battles in the West (Box 4)
  - Maps of areas in Montana and Wyoming (Box 4, 14-21)
  - Miscellaneous Research Material (Box 9-10, 22-23)
  - Muster Rolls (photocopies) of U.S. regiments that served in the West (Box 11, 22-23)
  - Pamphlets about western history (Box 4)
  - Periodicals - Magazine Clipping about western history, 1876-1962 (Box 4-5)
  - Periodicals - "Little Big Horn Associates Newsletter", 1967-1968 (Box 5)
  - Periodicals - Newspapers and Newspaper Clippings, 1876-1967 (Box 5)
  - Prints - Company of Military Collectors & Historians Plate nos. 201-212, 214-220, 215 (Box 11)
  - Reprints of articles about western military history, 1926-1965 (Box 6)
  - Research Notes (Box 6-8)
  - Scrapbook of newspaper clippings - "Excerpts from John Hunton's Diary" (Box 11)
- Series II. Photographs
  Includes copy prints of historic photographs, as well as photographs taken by J.W. Vaughn and others of historic battle sites.
  - Art, undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Art – Remington Illustrations, undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Art – Schreyvogel Illustrations, undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Bullet Shells, undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Crook’s Column, 1876, undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Crook’s Column, 1876 – Maps and Newspaper Illustrations, undated (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Fort C.F. Smith, 1968 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Fort Fetterman, undated (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Fort Laramie Hog Corrals and Area, 1963 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Fort Phil Kearney, 1968, undated (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Fort Reno, undated (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - “Forty-Niner Trail”, 1963 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Indian Battles – Beecher’s Island, 1868, undated (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Indian Battles – Cloud Peak Campsite, 1876, undated (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Indian Battles – Dry Fork of Cheyenne Campsite, 1876, undated (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Indian Battles – Fetterman, 1866, 1962, undated (Box 12, Folder 16-20)
  - Indian Battles – Hay Field, 1867, undated (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Indian Battles – Little Big Horn, 1876, undated (Box 12, Folder 22-31)
  - Indian Battles – Reynolds, 1876, undated (Box 12, Folder 32-35)
  - Indian Battles – Rosebud, 1876, undated (Box 12, Folder 36-40)
  - Indian Battles – Sage Creek Campsite, 1876, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Indian Battles – Sand Creek, 1864, undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Indian Battles – Skeleton Cave (Arizona), 1872, 1963 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Indian Battles – Summit Springs, 1869, 1962-1963 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Indian Battles – Unidentified, 1963-1966, undated (Box 13, Folder 5-13)
  - Indian Battles – Wagon Box, 1867, 1934, undated (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Indian Battles – Western U.S. – Maps, undated (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Indian Battles – Wounded Knee, 1890, undated (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Jackson, William Henry – Works of (Independence Rock; Three Crossings Station), undated (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Mules, undated (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - People – Cheyenne Indians (Bald Bear and Cut Foot; Comes In Sight; Dull Knife; Lame White Man; Olvit; Roman Nose?; Spotted Wolf; Tall Bull, Jacob; Two Moons; White Shield; etc.), undated (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - People – Crow Indians (Medicine Crow; Old Crow; Plenty Coups; E.S. Curtis images; etc.), undated (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - People – Dakota Indians (Black Bear; Black Bird; Crazy Horse? and Crazy Horse Butte; Gall; Hump; Kicking Bear; Little Big Man; One Bull; Sitting Bull; Spotted Bear; White Bull; etc.), undated (Box 13, Folder 22)
  - People – Indians (Unidentified), undated (Box 13, Folder 23)
  - People – Kiowa Indians (Setank), undated (Box 13, Folder 24)
  - People – Officers, A-N, undated (Box 13, Folder 25)
  - People – Officers, P-Z, undated (Box 13, Folder 26)
  - People – Officers, Groups, undated (Box 13, Folder 27)
  - People – Scouts and Other Civilians, undated (Box 13, Folder 28)
  - People – Shoshone Indians (Tyhee; Washakie; etc.), undated (Box 13, Folder 29)
  - People – Soldiers (A.J. Custard; Dennis Driscoll; John A. Kirkwood; George McAnulty; etc.), undated (Box 13, Folder 30)
  - People – Vaughn, Jesse Wendell, 1953-1968 (Box 13, Folder 31)
  - People – Vaughn’s Family and Friends, 1953-1968 (Box 13, Folder 32)
  - Pinkerton Reports on Harvey Logan, 1902, undated (Box 13, Folder 33)
  - Wagon Drawings, undated (Box 13, Folder 34)
  - Copy Negatives from Books, Newspapers, Photographs, etc., undated (Box 13, Folder 35)
  - Copy Negatives – Maps and Newspaper Illustrations, undated (Box 13, Folder 36)
  - Negatives - Indian Battle Sites, circa 1950s-circa 1960s (Box 13, Folder 37-38)
  - Negatives - Vaughn, Family, and Friends, circa 1950s-circa 1960s (Box 13, Folder 39)